Preliminary Guide to the Collection of Nineteenth-Century Graphic Art
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Nineteenth-Century Graphic Art
1800-1899
AOB 77
Yale University Arts Library
1
(3 boxes + 1 broadside drawer)
This collection contains examples of graphic art from 1800-1899. Many of these materials are not dated; an educated guess as to the age of the material was based on paper type and subject matter.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Collection of Nineteenth-Century Graphic Art was housed in the former Arts of the Book Collection until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains examples of graphic art from 1800-1899. Many of these materials are not dated; an educated guess as to the age of the material was based on paper type and subject matter.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Figurative: Groups. II. Figurative: Portraits and Single Subjects. III. Landscape & Architecture. IV. Nature. V. Ornamentation. VI. Typography and Advertising.
Broadsides -- Specimens; Graphic arts; Letterpress printing -- Specimens.; Intaglio printing -- Specimens.; Prints; Relief prints; Intaglio prints; Letterpress printing; Broadside
- Figurative: Groups, Series I
  - Depictions of groups, plus two multi-part "murals" including Bayeux tapestry reproduction., 19th century; 59 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Depictions of groups., 19th century; 31 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Figurative: Portraits and Single Subjects, Series II
  - Portraits and/or single subjects., 19th century; 96 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portraits and/or single subjects., 19th century; 17 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Portraits and/or single subjects., 19th century; 4 (Folder 1)
- Landscape & Architecture, Series III
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes scenes of life in and around buildings. It also includes seascapes.
  - Depictions of landscape and/or architecture., 19th century; 62 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Depictions of landscape and/or architecture., 19th century; 14 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Nature, Series IV
  Of significant note are depictions of race horses and a series of lunar maps.
  - Depictions of nature., 19th century; 53 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Depictions of nature., 19th century; 4 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "The American Agriculturalist", 1866 (Folder 1)
  - Views of lunar, solar, & meteorological events., 1875-1881; 5 (Folder 1)
  - "General karte der sichtbaren seite der mondoberflaeche…", 1837; 4 (Folder 1)
- Ornamentation, Series V
  - Depictions of ornamentation., 19th century; 19 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Typography and Advertising, Series VI
  - Examples of typography and/or advertising., 19th century; 114 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Examples of typography and/or advertising., 19th century; 14 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "The great western United States mail route", 1852 (Folder 1)
  - "The Cincinnati Weekly Times", undated (Folder 1)
  - "A newly invented chronological chart of British nobility", 1808 (Folder 1)